Albert E. Waugh Papers 1988.0059
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Libraries
Albert E. Waugh Papers
undated, 1924-1984
1988.0059
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Libraries
23.5 Linear feet
Personal and professional papers, notebooks, and photographs of Albert E. Waugh, Professor and administrator at the University of Connecticut from 1924 until his retirement in 1965. Materials document his career, political activities, research interests and retirement.
Waugh, Albert E.
Scope and Content Note
The collection contains the personal and professional papers of UConn professor Albert E. Waugh. The papers include professional papers such as convention journals, bulletins, positions taken, and addresses made to the academic conventions. Among the professional papers in the collection are many of Albert Waugh's publications. Included among them is his Master's Thesis, "A Basis for the Computation of Index Numbers of Prices of Farm Products in Connecticut." There are also scrapbooks containing newspaper clippings which relate to Waugh's research, as well as lecture notes and aids used by Waugh during his economics and mathematics lectures. The collection also features a large collection of photographs taken by Waugh, documenting the campus and university events from the 1930s to the 1960s. Among the photographs are images of the campus, banquets celebrating the 50th anniversary of the University, President Jorgensen's inauguration, the opening of the College Theatre, and Trustees' meetings. The files also contain correspondence, both incoming and outgoing, and files devoted to particular people, projects, or events connected to Professor Waugh's interest in sundials.
Among the personal papers that make up the collection are numerous papers that provide valuable insight into Waugh's political views and activities, as well as the political activity in Connecticut during this period. Additionally, the collection contains numerous journals, keep by Waugh for more than four decades, containing Waugh's observations and comments on the University of Connecticut, the town of Storrs, and his family.
Biography
Albert E. Waugh was born in 1902 in Amherst, Massachusetts. He received a Bachelor of Science degree in economics from Massachusetts Agricultural College in 1924. He received a Master of Science degree in economics from Connecticut Agricultural College in 1926. He also attended Columbia University in 1925 and the University of Chicago in 1931-1932 and 1942-1943. Waugh was hired as an instructor of agricultural economics at Connecticut Agricultural College in 1924. He was promoted to Assistant Professor in 1928, Associate Professor in 1932, and Professor in 1937. He served as head of the Department of Economics from 1939 to 1945,and Dean of the College of Arts and Sciences from 1945 to 1950. He became Provost of the University of Connecticut in 1950, and served in that position until he retired in 1965.
In 1938, Waugh published the textbook, Elements of Statistical Method, and its accompanying laboratory manual. The text was translated into Portugese in 1946; and in 1947, he published Principles of Economics. He also served on many university committees; including Scholastic Standards, of which he was chairman; The Committee on Athletics; Curricula and Courses Committee; Senate Salary Committee; and Advisory Committee to the President. He was also a member of the University Senate, elected and ex-officio, during most of his years at the University.
In addition to his University commitments, Waugh was also a member of the American Economic Society, the American Academy of Arts and Sciences, the American Association of University Professors, and Phi Kappa Phi. He was an active member of his community as well, serving on the Board of Trustees of the Windham Community Memorial Hospital, and as Director of the Willimantic Trust Company. He was well known as the moderator of Mansfield Town Meetings, a service he began in 1941. He served on a number of State commissions; and in 1965, he was chosen by the Republican Party to attend the State Constitutional Convention.
Dr. Waugh died in 1985 at the age of 82.
Arrangement
Series I: Constitutional Convention ( 1965 ). Albert Waugh's deep interest in politics was rewarded when he was selected by the Republican Party for Connecticut's Constitutional Convention in 1965. Included in Series I are working papers such as convention journals, bulletins, positions taken, and addresses made to the convention. Also here is a personal scrapbook containing numerous newspaper clippings which relate to the Convention meetings and resolutions.
Series II: University of Connecticut ( 1930-1965 ) is organized in four subseries: President Babbidge, Lecture Notes/Aids, Photographs, and Retirement. President Babbidge consists of materials on the President's inauguration on 20 October 1962, including a program of the inauguration ceremony and a special issue magazine commemorating the event. Lecture Notes/Aids contains notes and aids used by Waugh during his economics and mathematics lectures. Included are notes related to the operation of an abacus; worksheets for computing planetarium projected settings; worksheets for determining time from the height of the sun; a large circular slide rule; lecture notes on parliamentary practice; lecture notes from Economics 111, 112, and 221; and old forms of currency, both paper and coin, indicating his deep interest in numismatics, and class grade books. In addition, Mr. Waugh's popularity as an educator is evident in this subseries. Photographs, ca. 1930-1960, contains photographs of the campus, banquets celebrating the 50th anniversary of the University, President Jorgensen's inauguration, the opening of the College Theatre, and Trustees' meetings. Retirement contains the most valuable material of the papers, consisting of citations, correspondence, State newspaper clippings, all of which pay tribute to Waugh's career at the University of Connecticut. This subseries provides not only excellent biographical material, but also a summary of his legendary activities. The significance of this material lies in its ability to illustrate the respect which Waugh's work generated in the community. The documentation of Mr. Waugh's tenure as Provost is located in the Provost's Office Records.
Series III: Writings and Personal ( undated, 1924-1968 ) contains some of Albert Waugh's writings. Among them are his Master's Thesis, "A Basis for the Computation of Index Numbers of Prices of Farm Products in Connecticut"; articles which appeared in various publications; notes from his many speeches; and copies of other speeches. Contained in the Personal subseries are jottings entitled "Day by Day", along with obituaries and a newspaper clipping concerning his brother, artist Sidney Waugh. The subseries Writings provides an appreciation of Waugh's competence as a writer; and his personal recollections, which resemble a diary, supply an intimate glimpse of the man himself.
Series IV: Political Correspondence ( 1938-1952 ) includes correspondence between Waugh and Governor Baldwin, and other prominent political figures in Connecticut. Included in the correspondence are discussions of party affiliations, reasons for supporting candidates, attitudes toward government actions, and reactions to legislation. This series provides valuable insight into Waugh's political views and activities, as well as the political activity in Connecticut during this period.
Series V: Daily Journal ( 1941-1983 ) includes volumes which cover the years that Waugh was employed at the university. The journals contain Waugh's observations and comments on the University of Connecticut, the town of Storrs, and his family.
Series VI: Sundials ( undated, 1929-1984 ) includes alphabetically arranged subject files covering several aspects of Albert Waugh's interest in sundials. The majority of documents are dated, and nearly all of these run from the late 1950s to 1984. Prof. Waugh's knowledge of sundials, and sundial books, was well developed by the 1950s. The files consist of correspondence, both incoming and outgoing, and files devoted to particular people, projects, or events connected to Prof. Waugh's interest in sundials. Notable folders include those from his co-enthusiast, and later friend Kenneth Lynch, a metalworker from western Connecticut who manufactured sundials and armillary spheres, those on Prof. Waugh's work on a sundial for the planetarium at Mystic Seaport in the early 1960s, and folders on the design and construction, and the dedication of the Waugh sundial at the University of Connecticut in Storrs. Perhaps most important are the folders devoted to his book, Sundials: Their Theory and Construction. It is clear from the correspondence that this book made him a leading figure among sundial enthusiasts, who offered their admiration and sought his advice. Finally, a few folders include horological calculations, often for unknown purposes.
Series VII: Astronomy (1970, 1972) contains Prof. Waugh's two notebooks, similar in internal structure and content, and with meticulous penmanship, each of which chronicled an expedition by automobile to observe a solar eclipse. Each spiral-bound notebook, in a separate folder, contains a travel log, and records of the eclipse itself. A third folder contains black and white prints of the same size, found with the notebooks, and labelled on the rear with exposure data. One clearly depicts a comet, and the others may depict multiple exposures of the Sun.
Series VIII: Surveying (undated) contains papers from one or more surveying projects Prof. Waugh conducted on or around his property in Storrs, Connecticut. Some of the papers have dates from the 1950s and 1960s. The folders' contents include measurements, sketches, and printed maps of the town of Mansfield.
Access
The collection is open and available for research.
Acquisition Information
The collection was donated by Mrs. Waugh in 1985. Daily Journal (1974-1983) materials were donated by Dr. John Waugh in 2010.
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of materials pertaining to the University, its history, administration, faculty, staff and students. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the Reading Room desk.
University of Connecticut.; Waugh, Albert E.; Archives.; Correspondence.; Diaries.; Educators.; Manuscripts.; Notebooks.; Photographs.; Publications.; Storrs (Conn.); University of Connecticut.
- Series I: Constitutional Convention, 1965
  - Correspondence and notes (Box 1)
  - Correspondence and notes (Box 1)
  - Revised constitution and constitutional index (Box 1)
  - Pamphlets and journals (Box 2)
  - Pamphlets and journals (Box 3)
  - Pamphlets and journals (Box 4)
  - Scrapbook (Box 5)
  - Photograph (Box 5)
  - Memorabilia (Box 5)
- Series II: University of Connecticut, undated, 1930-1965
  - President Babbidge (Box 6)
    - Inauguration material, 1962 (Box 6)
  - Lecture Notes and Aids, undated
    - Lecture Notes (Box 7)
    - Lecture Notes (Box 8)
    - Artifacts, undated
      - Abacus (Box 9)
      - Paper money and coins (Box 9)
      - Circular slide rule (Box 9)
  - Photographs, 1930-1960 (Box 6)
  - Retirement, 1965 (Box 6)
- Series III: Writings and Personal, undated, 1924-1968
  - Diary, undated (Box 10)
  - Diary, undated (Box 10)
  - Diary, undated (Box 10)
  - Publications, 1934-1968 (Box 11)
  - Speeches, 1964-1967 (Box 11)
  - Sidney Waugh, 1964 (Box 11)
  - Time keeping, 1966 (Box 11)
  - Notes, 1934-1968 (Box 12)
  - Proclamations of Wilbur Cross, 1937 (Box 13)
  - Commonplace book (Box 13)
  - Master's thesis, 1924 (Box 13)
  - Baseball scorebook, 1947 (Box 13)
- Series IV: Political Correspondence, 1938-1952
  - Alcorn, Hugh Mead, 1938-1952 (Box 14)
  - Baldwin, Raymond, 1938-1952 (Box 14)
  - Danaher, John, 1938-1944 (Box 14)
  - Harwood, Benjamin, 1938-1939 (Box 14)
  - McConaughty, James, 1938 (Box 14)
  - Smith, Edwin O., 1942-1952 (Box 14)
  - Smith, Fred, 1949 (Box 14)
  - General, 1938-1952 (Box 14)
- Series V: Daily Journal, 1941-1983
  - Daily Journal, 1941-1946 (Box 15)
    - Index, 1941
    - 1941 January
    - 1941 February
    - 1941 March
    - 1941 April
    - 1941 May
    - 1941 June
    - 1941 July
    - 1941 August
    - 1941 September
    - 1941 October
    - 1941 November
    - 1941 December
    - Index, 1942
    - 1942 January
    - 1942 February
    - 1942 March
    - 1942 April
    - 1942 May
    - 1942 June
    - 1942 July
    - 1942 August
    - 1942 September
    - 1942 October
    - 1942 November
    - 1942 December
    - 1943 January
    - 1943 January 29 - March 20
    - 1943 March 21 - April 14
    - 1943 April 15 - May 17
    - 1943 May 18 - June 22
    - 1943 June 23 - August 13
    - 1943 August 14 - October 2
    - 1943 October 3 - November 6
    - 1943 November 7 - December 31
    - 1944 January 1-28
    - 1944 January 29 - February 24
    - 1944 February 25 - March 31
    - 1944 April 1 - May 15
    - 1944 May 16 - June 17
    - 1944 June 18 - July 28
    - 1944 July 29 - August 29
    - 1944 August 30- October 3
    - 1944 October 4 - November 3
    - 1944 November 4 - December 7
    - 1944 December 8-31
    - 1945 January 1 - February 2
    - 1945 February 3 - March 5
    - 1945 March 6 - April 16
    - 1945 April 17 - May 26
    - 1945 May 27 - July 7
    - 1945 July 8 - August 15
    - 1945 August 16 - September 15
    - 1945 September 16 - Octobe r16
    - 1945 October 17 - November 15
    - 1945 November 16 - December 6
    - 1945 December 7-31
    - 1946 Jaunary 1 - February 7
    - 1946 February 8 - March 26
    - 1946 March 27 - May 7
    - 1946 May 8 - June 8
    - 1946 June 9 - July 22
    - 1946 July 23 - August 30
    - 1946 August 31 - October 11
    - 1946 October 12 - November 22
    - 1946 November 23 - December 31
    - 1947 January 1 - February 5
    - 1947 February 6 - March 17
    - 1947 March 18 - May 2
    - 1947 May 3 - June 6
    - 1947 June 7 - July 6
    - 1947 July 7 - August 16
    - 1947 August 17 - September 12
    - 1947 September 13 - October 6
    - 1947 October 7 - November 8
    - 1947 November 9 - December 5
    - 1948 January 1 - February 22
    - 1948 February 23 - April 9
    - 1948 April 10 - May 24
    - 1948 May 25 - July 3
    - 1948 July 4 - August 21
    - 1948 August 22 - October 4
    - 1948 October 5 - November 15
    - 1948 November 16 - December 31
    - 1949 January 1 - February 14
    - 1949 February 15 - April 3
    - 1949 April 4 - May 21
    - 1949 May 22 - July 18
    - 1949 July 19 - September 25
    - 1949 September 26 - November 9
    - 1949 November 10 - December 31
    - 1950 January 1 - February 19
    - 1950 February 20 - April 15
    - 1950 April 16 - June 11
    - 1950 June 12 - August 17
    - 1950 August 18 - October 25
    - 1950 October 26 - December 31
    - 1951 January 1 - February 13
    - 1951 February 14 - April 6
    - 1951 April 7 - May 19
    - 1951 May 20 - July 11
    - 1951 July 12 - September 11
    - 1951 September 12 - October 17
    - 1951 October 18 - November 17
    - 1951 November 18 - December 31
    - 1952 January 1 - February 18
    - 1952 February 19 - April 8
    - 1952 April 9 - June 1
    - 1952 June 2 - August 5
    - 1952 August 6 - September 21
    - 1952 September 22 - November 1
    - 1952 November 2 - December 11
    - 1952 December 12 - 31
    - 1953 January 1 - February 9
    - 1953 February 10 - March 20
    - 1953 March 21 - April 22
    - 1953 April 23 - May 21
    - 1953 May 22 - July 11
    - 1953 July 12 - September 1
    - 1953 September 2 - October 18
    - 1953 October 19 - November 30
    - 1953 December
    - 1954 January 1 - February 8
    - 1954 February 9 - March 22
    - 1954 March 23 - May 1
    - 1954 May 2 - June 18
    - 1954 June 19 - August 7
    - 1954 August 8 - September 25
    - 1954 September 26 - November 16
    - 1954 November 17 - December 31
    - Index, 1955
    - 1955 January 1 - February 13
    - 1955 February 14 - March 30
    - 1955 March 31 - May 4
    - 1955 May 5 - June 21
    - 1955 June 22 - August 15
    - 1955 August 16 - October 3
    - 1955 October 4 - November 23
    - 1955 November 24 - December 31
    - 1956 January 1 - February 15
    - 1956 February 16 - April 4
    - 1956 April 5 - May 30
    - 1956 May 31 - July 26
    - 1956 July 27 - September 17
    - 1956 September 18 - November 19
    - 1956 November 20 - December 31
    - 1957 January 1 - February 15
    - 1957 February 16 - April 10
    - 1957 April 11 - June 11
    - 1957 June 12 - August 10
    - 1957 August 11 - October 10
    - 1957 October 11 - November 12
    - 1957 November 13 - December 10
    - 1957 December 11-31
    - 1958 January 1-25
    - 1958 January 26 - February 22
    - 1958 February 23 - April 3
    - 1958 April 4 - May 10
    - 1958 May 11 - June 22
    - 1958 June 23 - August 2
    - 1958 August 3 - September 10
    - 1958 September 11 - October 19
    - 1958 October 20 - December 3
    - 1958 December 4-31
    - 1959 January 1 - February 4
    - 1959 February 5 - March 23
    - 1959 March 24 - May 4
    - 1959 May 5 - June 13
    - 1959 June 14 - July 31
    - 1959 August 1 - September 23
    - 1959 September 24 - November 10
    - 1959 November 11 - December 31
    - 1960 January 1 - February 11
    - 1960 February 12 - March 28
    - 1960 March 29 - May 17
    - 1960 May 18 - July 3
    - 1960 July 4 - August 19
    - 1960 Agust 20 - October 2
    - 1960 October 3 - November 16
    - 1960 November 17 - December 31
    - 1961 January 1 - February 13
    - 1961 February 14 - March 22
    - 1961 March 23 - April 30
    - 1961 May 1 - June 21
    - 1961 June 22 - August 12
    - 1961 August 13 - September 25
    - 1961 September 26 - October 25
    - 1961 October 26 - December 3
    - 1961 December 4-31
    - 1962 January 1 - February 16
    - 1962 February 17 - April 11
    - 1962 April 12 - May 27
    - 1962 May 28 - July 18
    - 1962 July 19 - September 5
    - 1962 September 6 - October 20
    - 1962 October 21 - December 12
    - 1962 December 13-31
    - 1963 January 1 - February 5
    - 1963 February 6 - March 16
    - 1963 March 17 - April 30
    - 1963 May 1 - June 14
    - 1963 June 15 - August 3
    - 1963 August 4 - September 22
    - 1963 September 23 - November 1
    - 1963 November 2 - December 31
    - 1964 January 1 - February 11
    - 1964 February 12 - April 8
    - 1964 April 9 - May 23
    - 1964 May 24 - July 9
    - 1964 July 10 - August 27
    - 1964 August 28 - October 15
    - 1964 October 16 - December 6
    - 1964 December 7-31
    - 1965 January 1 - February 11
    - 1965 February 12 - March 29
    - 1965 March 30 - May 14
    - 1965 June 18 - July 31
    - 1965 August 1 - September 15
    - 1965 September 16 - October 19
    - 1965 October 20 - November 9
    - 1965 November 10 - December 19
    - 1965 December 20-31
    - 1966 January 1 - February 10
    - 1966 February 11 - March 27
    - 1966 March 28 - May 14
    - 1966 May 15 - June 18
    - 1966 June 19 - August 3
    - 1966 August 4 - September 19
    - 1966 September 20 - November 3
    - 1966 November 4 - December 23
    - 1966 December 24-31
    - 1967 January 1 - February 1
    - 1967 February 2 - March 12
    - 1967 March 13 - April 18
    - 1967 April 19 - May 28
    - 1967 May 29 - July 9
    - 1967 July 10 - August 15
    - 1967 August 16 - September 30
    - 1967 October 1-29
    - 1967 October 30 - November 30
    - 1967 December
    - 1968 January 1 - February 4
    - 1968 February 5 - March 7
    - 1968 March 8 - April 2
    - 1968 April 3 - May 10
    - 1968 May 11 - June 14
    - 1968 June 15 - July 29
    - 1968 July 30 - September 10
    - 1968 September 11 - October 15
    - 1968 October 16 - November 23
    - 1968 November 24 - December 31
    - 1969 January 1 - February 4
    - 1969 February 5 - March 19
    - 1969 March 20 - May 5
    - 1969 May 6 - June 19
    - 1969 June 20 - July 23
    - 1969 July 24 - September 4
    - 1969 September 5 - October 24
    - 1969 October 25 - December 4
    - 1969 December 5-31
  - Daily Journal, 1946-1953 (Box 16)
  - Daily Journal, 1953-1959 (Box 17)
  - Daily Journal, 1960-1965 (Box 18)
  - Daily Journal, 1966-1969 (Box 19)
  - Daily Journal, 1974-1975 (Box 26)
  - Daily Journal, 1976-1979 October (Box 27)
  - Daily Journal, 1979 October - 1983 (Box 28)
- Series VI: Sundials, undated, 1929-1984
  - A, undated, 1964-1977 (Box 20, Folder 278)
  - Armillary Spheres, undated, 1971, 1975 (Box 20, Folder 279)
  - Articles
    - Journals, undated, 1929, 1954-1972 (Box 20, Folder 280)
    - Scientific American, 1951-1959, 1966, 1974 (Box 20, Folder 281)
  - B - Bernhardt, Martin, undated, 1966, 1972-1976 (Box 20, Folder 282)
  - Behrendt, Hans, undated, 1972-1980 (Box 20, Folder 283)
  - Basic Data for Requisites of Dials, undated (Box 20, Folder 284)
  - Blume, Gosta - Burt, Edwin, undated, 1966-1981 (Box 20, Folder 285)
  - Blueprints, Rubbings, and Maps, undated, 1959 (Box 20, Folder 286)
  - Book Collecting, 1943, 1959-1960 (Box 20, Folder 287)
  - Book Collecting, 1961-1970 (Box 20, Folder 288)
  - C, undated, 1975-1984 (Box 20, Folder 289)
  - D - F, 1957-1983 (Box 20, Folder 290)
  - Dover Publications: Letters Forwarded, 1974-1983 (Box 20, Folder 291)
  - G - L, 1970, 1973-1980 (Box 21, Folder 292)
  - Gyles, Henry (Sundial), 1982, 1984 (Box 21, Folder 293)
  - Instruments, undated, 1959, 1972 (Box 21, Folder 294)
  - Lynch, Kenneth
    - Blueprint, undated (Oversize 1)
    - Correspondence, undated, 1950, 1957-1976 (Box 21, Folder 295)
    - Correspondence, 1977-1982 (Box 21, Folder 296)
    - Letters Forwarded, 1975-1976 (Box 21, Folder 297)
    - Letters Forwarded, 1978, 1980-1981 (Box 21, Folder 298)
  - M, 1949, 1963-1975 (Box 21, Folder 299)
  - Maps, undated, 1959-1965 (Oversize 1)
  - Mitchell, R. Mark, undated, 1979-1980 (Box 21, Folder 300)
  - Mystic Seaport, undated, 1959, 1961 (Box 21, Folder 301)
  - Mystic Seaport, 1962-1966, 1969 (Box 21, Folder 302)
  - N - P, undated, 1963, 1973-1979 (Box 22, Folder 303)
  - Newspaper Clippings, undated, 1962-1974 (Box 22, Folder 304)
  - Newspapers, 1939, 1974-1976 (Box 22, Folder 305)
  - Nocturnal, undated, 1962 (Box 22, Folder 306)
  - Notes and Directions, undated (Box 22, Folder 307)
  - Notes and Directions, undated (Box 22, Folder 308)
  - Notes and Directions, undated (Box 22, Folder 309)
  - Permission to Reproduce Illustrations and Photographs, 1960, 1969-1971 (Box 22, Folder 310)
  - Photographs
    - A - Lynch, Kenneth, undated (Box 22, Folder 311)
    - M - Z (Box 22, Folder 312)
    - Mariners Museum, [1959] (Box 22, Folder 313)
  - Photographs, Postcards, and Cards: Unidentified, undated, 1962-1973 (Box 22, Folder 314)
  - Q - S, 1960-1982 (Box 23, Folder 315)
  - Revised Chapter 13, undated (Box 23, Folder 316)
  - Sawyer, Frederick W., III, 1975-1976, 1978 (Box 23, Folder 317)
  - Sketches: Animals, undated, 1964 (Box 23, Folder 318)
  - Slide Lecture Notes, undated-1982 (Box 23, Folder 319)
  - Slides
    - Sundials, undated (Box 22, Folder 320)
    - Timekeeping, undated (Box 22, Folder 321)
  - Sundial Journals
    - Formulas, undated (Box 24, Folder 338)
    - Skiagrapher's Handbook of Gnomonical Information, undated (Box 24, Folder 339)
    - Skiagrapher's Information, undated (Box 24, Folder 340)
    - Skiagrapher's Information, undated (Box 24, Folder 341)
  - Sundials
    - Collecting, undated, 1958-1960 (Box 23, Folder 322)
    - Collecting, 1961-1963, 1969, 1971 (Box 23, Folder 323)
    - Designs (formerly "Current Chapter"), undated, 1960-1963 (Box 23, Folder 324)
    - Designs (formerly "Sundials - N.O.I.B.N."), undated, 1939-1945, 1970-1971 (Box 23, Folder 325)